<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Killing noe murder. Briefly discoursed in three quæstions. By William Allen.</title>
            <author>Titus, Silius, 1623?-1704.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 81 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94382</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1310</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E501_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203800</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863618</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863618</idno>
            <idno type="VID">164183</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94382)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 164183)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 79:E501[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Killing noe murder. Briefly discoursed in three quæstions. By William Allen.</title>
                  <author>Titus, Silius, 1623?-1704.</author>
                  <author>Allen, William, Adjutant-general of the army in Ireland, attributed name.</author>
                  <author>Sexby, Edward, d. 1658.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Holland :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In fact by Silius Titus and Edward Sexby.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 1657".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Despotism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Monarchy --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Regicides --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:164183:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Killing Noe Murder. Briefly Diſcourſt in Three Quaeſtions.</head>
            <byline>By WILLIAM ALLEN.</byline>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>And all the people of the Land rejoyced: and the City was quiet, after that they had ſlain Athaliah with the Sword.</p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2.</hi> Chro. <hi>23.21.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <p>Now after the time that Amaziah did turn away from following the Lord, they made a Conſpiracie againſt him in Ieruſalem, and he fled to Lachish: but they ſent to Lachish after him, and ſlew him there.</p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2.</hi> Chro. <hi>25.27.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To his Highneſſe, OLIVER CROMWELL,</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>May it pleaſe your Highneſſe:</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ow I have ſpent ſome howers of the leaſure your Highnes hath been pleaſed to give me, this following Paper will give your Highnes an accompt. How you will pleaſe to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret it I can not tell, but I can with confidence ſay, my intention in it is, to procure your Highnes that juſtice no body yet does you and to let the people ſee, the longer they deferr it the greater injury they doe both themſelves and you: To your Highnes justly belongs the honour of dying for the people, and it cannot chooſe but be an unſpeakable conſolation to you in the laſt moments of your life, to conſider, with how much benefit to the world you are like to leave it.
'Tis then onely (my Lord) the titles you now uſurpe will be truly yours, you wil then be indeed the delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of your Countrey, &amp; free it from a Bondage little inferiour to that from which Moyſes delivered his. You will then be that true Reformer, which you would now be thought. Religion shalbe then reſtored, Liberty aſſerted and Parliaments have thoſe Priviledges they have fought for We shall then hope that other Lawes will have place beſides thoſe of the Sword and that Iuſtice shalbe otherwiſe defind then the will &amp; pleaſure of the ſtrongeſt, and we shal then hope men wil keep oathes again, and not have the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of being falſe, and Perfidious to preſerve themſelves and be like their Rulers. All this we hope from your Highnes happie expirat on, who are the true Father of your Countrie for while you live we can call nothing ours, and it is from your death that we hope for our inheritances. Let this conſideration arme and fortifie your Highneſſes minde against the feares of death, and the terrours of your evil Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that the good you will doe by your death, wil ſomething ballance the evils of your life. And if in the Black Catalogue of High Malefactours, few can be found that have lived more to the affliction and diſturbance of mankind, then your Highnes hath done yet your greatest enemies wil not deny but there are likewiſe as few that have expired more to the univerſall ben fit of mankind then your Highn: is like to doe. To haſten this great good is the chief end of my writing this Paper and if it have the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, I hope it will your Highnes wil quickly be out of the reach of mens malice and your enemies will only be able to wound you in your memory, which strokes you will not feel. That your Highneſſe may be ſpeedily in this ſecurity is the univerſall wishes of your gratefull Countrey. This is the deſires and prayers of the good and of the bad and it may be if the only thing wherein al Sects, and factions do agree in their devotions, and is our onely common prayer. But amongſt all that put in their Requeſts and ſupplications for your Highneſſes ſpeedy deliverance from al earthly troubles, none is more aſsidu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, nor more fervent then he, that with the reſt of the Nation hath the Honour to be</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>May it pleaſe your Highneſſe:</salute>
                  <signed>Your Highneſſe preſent Slave and Vaſſall. <hi>W. A.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:164183:2"/>
               <head>To all thoſe Officers and Soldiers of the Army, that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member their ingagements, and dare be honeſt.</head>
               <p>I Heartily wish for Englands ſake, that your number may be farre greater then I fear it is; and that his Highnes his frequent pargations may have left any amongſt you that by theſe Characters are concern'd in this Dedication. That I and all men have reaſon to make this a doubt, your own actions, as well as your tame ſufferings do but too plainly manifeſt. For you that were the Champions of our Liberty, and to that purpoſe were raiſed, are not you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the inſtruments of our Slavery? and your hands that the people employ'd to take off the yoake from of our necks, are not thoſe the very hands that now doe put it on? Doe you remember that you were raiſed to defend the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of Parliament, and have ſworn to doe it; and will you be employed to force Elections, and diſſolve Parlements, becauſe they will not eſtablish the Tyrants iniquity, and our ſlavery by a Law? I beſeech you think upon what you have promiſed and what you doe, and give not Poſterity as well as your own Generation the occaſion to mention you with infamie, and to curſe that unfortunate valour, and ſucceſſe of yours, that onely hath gained victories (as you uſe them) againſt the common-wealth. Could ever England have thought to have ſeen that Armie that was never mentioned without the titles of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, Zealous, Faithfull, Conragious, the fence of her libertie at home, the Terrour of her enemies abroad; Become her Gaolers? not her Guard, but her oppreſſours? not her Souldiers, but a Tyrants executioners, drawing to blocks and gibbets all that dare be honeſter then themſelves? This you doe, and this you are; nor can you ever redeem your own honour, the truſt and love of your Countrie, the eſtimation of brave men, or the praiers of good; If you let not ſpeedilie the world ſee you have been deceived; which they will onelie then beleeve, when they ſee your vengeance upon his Faithleſſe head that did it. This if you deferr too long to doe, you will finde too late to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, and your Repentance will neither vindicate you, nor help us. To let you ſee you may doe this as a lawfull action, and to perſwade you to it as a Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious one, is the principall intent of this following Paper: Which, what ever effects it hath upon you, I shall not abſolutely fail of my ends; for if it excites not your vertue and Courage, it will yet exprobrate your Cowardice and Baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. This is from one that was once one amongſt you, and will be ſo again when you dare be as you were.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:164183:2"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not any Ambition to be in Print, when ſo few ſpare Paper and the Preſſe, nor any inſtigations of private revenge or malice (though ſew that dare be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt now want their cauſes) that have prevailed with me to make my ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Authour of a Pamplet, and to diſturbe that Quiet which at preſent I enjoy, by his Highnes great favour and injuſtice. Nor am I ignorant to how little purpoſe I shall imploy that time and paines, which I shal beſtow upon this Paper. For to thinck that any reaſons or perſwaſions of mine, or convictions of their own, ſhall draw men from any thing wherein they ſee profit or ſecurity, or to any thing wherein they fear loſſe, or ſee dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, is to have a better opinion both of my ſelf and them, then either of us both deſerve.</p>
               <p>Beſides, the ſubject it ſelf is of that nature, that I am not onely to expect danger from ill men, but cenſure and diſallowance from many that are good; for theſe opinions only lookt upon, not lookt into (which all have not eyes for) will appear bloody and cruel; &amp; theſe compellations I muſt expect from thoſe that have a zeal, but not according to knowledge: If therefore I had conſidered my ſelf, I had ſpared what ever this is of paines, and not diſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted ſo many, to pleaſe ſo few, as are in mankinde, (the honeſt and the wiſe.) But at ſuch a time as this, when God is not onely exerciſing vs with a uſuall and common calamitie, of letting us fall into ſlavery, that uſed our liberty ſo ill; but is pleaſed ſo farr to blinde our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings, and to debaſe our ſpirits, as to ſuffer us to court our bondage, and to place it amongſt the requeſts we put up to him; Indignation makes a man break that ſilence that prudence would perſwade him to uſe; if not to work upon other mens mindes, yet to eaſe his own.</p>
               <p>A late Pamphlet tels us of a great deſigne diſcovered againſt the perſon of his Highnes &amp; of the Parlements comming (for ſo does that junto proſane that name) to congratulate with his Highnes, his happy deliverance from that wicked and bloody attempt. Beſides this that they have Ordered that God Almighty ſhalbe mockt with a day of thankſgiving (as I thinck the world is with the plot) &amp; that the people ſhal give publique thanks for the publique cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, that God is yet pleaſed to continue his judgements upon them, and to fruſtrate all meanes that are uſed for their deliverance: Certainly none will now deny that the Engliſh are a very thankfull people. But I thinck if we had read in Scripture that the Iſraelites had cryed unto the Lord, not for their own deliverance, but the preſervation of their Task ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and that they had thanked God with Solemnity that Pharaoh was yet living, and that there was ſtill great hopes of the daily encreaſe of the number of their Bricks: Though that people did ſo many things not onely impiouſly and profanely, but ridiculouſly and abſurdly, yet certainly they did nothing we ſhould more have wondered at, then to have found them Ceremoniouſly thankfull to God for plagues, that were commonly ſo brutiſhly unthankfull for mercies; And we ſhould have thought that Moyſes had done them a great deal of wrong, if he had not ſuffered them to enjoy their ſlavery and left them to their Tasks &amp; Garlick.</p>
               <p>I can with juſtice ſay my principal intention in this Paper is not to declaim againſt my L. <hi>Protectour</hi> or his Accompl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, for were it not more to juſtifie others then to accuſe them, I ſhould think their own actions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d that work ſufficiently, and I ſhould not take pains to tell the world what they know before. My deſigne is to examine whether if there hath been ſuch a plott as we heare of; and that it was contrived by Mr. <hi>Sindercombe</hi> againſt my <hi>L. Protectour,</hi> and not by my <hi>L Protectour</hi> againſt Mr. <hi>Sindercombe</hi> (which is doubtfull) whether it deſerves thoſe Epithites <hi>Mr. Speaker</hi> is pleaſed to give it, of bloody wicked, and proceeding from the Prince of darkneſſe. I know very well how uncapable the vulger are of conſidering what is extraordinary &amp; ſingular in every caſe, and that they judge of things, and name them by their exteriour appearances, without penetrating at all into their cauſes or natures. And without doubt when they heare the <hi>Protectour</hi> was to be kil'd, they ſtreight conclude a man was to be murdered, not a malefactour puniſhed: for they think the formalities do alwayes make the thing themſelves, and that tis the Judge and the Cryer that makes the juſtice, and the Goal the Criminall: And therfore when they read in the Pamplet <hi>Mr. Speakers</hi> ſpeech, they certainly think he gives theſe Plotters their right titles; and, as readily as a High-court of Juſtice, they condemn them, without ever examining whether they would have killed a Magiſtrate, or deſtroyed a Tyrant, over whom every man is naturally a Judge and an Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tioner; and whom the laws of God, of nature, and of nations expoſe, like Beaſts of prey, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be deſtroyed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s they are met.</p>
               <p>That I may be as plain as I can, I ſhall firſt make it a queſtion (which indeed is none) whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther my <hi>Lord Protectour</hi> be a Tyrant or not? Secondly, if he be. Whether it is lawfull to do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſtice upon him without Solemnitie, <hi>that is,</hi> to Kill him? Thirdly, if it be lawfull, Whether <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is like to prove profitable or noxious to the Common-wealth?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:164183:3"/>
               <p>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> makes Tyrants of two ſorts. <hi>Tirannus ſine Titulo</hi> and <hi>Tirannus Exercitio.</hi> The one is called a Tyrant becauſe he hath no right to govern,<note place="margin">Firſt. Quaſtion</note> the other becauſe he governs Tyrannically. We will very briefly diſcourſe of them both, and ſee whether the <hi>Protectour</hi> may not with great Juſtice put in his claim to both Titles.</p>
               <p>We ſhal fuſſiciently demonſtrate who they are that have not a right to govern, if we ſhew who they are that have; and what it is that makes the power juſt, which thoſe that rule, have over the naturall libertie of other men. To Fathers within their private Families nature hath given a Supreme power. Every man, ſayes Ariſtotle,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pol. l. <hi>1</hi> c. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </note> of Right governs his wife &amp; chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and this power was neceſſarily exerciſed<note n="(b)" place="margin">Gen. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>24</hi>
                  </note> every where, whilſt families lived di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſt,<note n="(c)" place="margin">Ariſt. ibid.</note> before the conſtitutions of Common-wealths; and in many places it continued after, as appeares by the laws of <hi>Solon,</hi> and the moſt Auncient of thoſe of Rome. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed as by the laws of God<note n="(d)" place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.8.</note> and nature, the care, defence, and ſupport of the family lies upon every man whoſe it is; ſo by the ſame law there is due unto every man from his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie a ſubjection and obedience, in compenſation of that ſupport. But ſeverall Families uniting themſelves together to make up one body of a Common-wealth, &amp; being Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent one of another, without any naturall Superioritie or obligation, nothing can introduce amongſt them a diſparitie of Rule and ſubjection, but ſome power that is over them; which power none can pretend to have but God and themſelves. Wherefore al power which is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully exerciſed over ſuch a ſocietie of men (which from the end of its inſtitution we call a Common wealth) muſt neceſſarily be derived either from the appointment of God Almi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghty,<note place="margin">Vid: Hooker Eccleſ. Pol. lib <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> who is ſupreme Lord of all &amp; every part; or from the conſent of the Society it ſelf, who have the next power to his, of diſpoſing of their own libertie, as they ſhal think fit for their own good. This power God hath given to ſocieties of men, as well as he gave it to particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ex.</hi> 21.5.</note> perſons, and when he interpoſes not his own authority and appoints not himſelf who ſhalbe his Vice-gerents and rule under him; he leaves it to none but the people themſelves to make the election, whoſe benefit is the end of all government. Nay when he himſelf hath been pleaſed to appoint rulers for that people, which he was pleaſed peculiarly to own, He many times made the choice, but left the Confirmation &amp; Ratification of that choice to the people themſelves. So Saul<note n="(f)" place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.1.</note> was choſen by God, and anointed King by his Prophet, but made King by all the people at Gilgal.<note n="(a)" place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.2.</note> David was anointed King<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Sam</hi> 16.14.</note> by the ſame Prophet but was afterwards, after Sauls death, confirmed by the people of Juda,<note n="(c)" place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.4</note> and 7. years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by the Elders of<note n="(d)" place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 5.3</note> Iſrael, the peoples deputies, at Chebron. And it is obſervable, that though they knew that David was appointed King by God &amp; anointed by his prophet, yet they likewiſe knew that God allowed to themſelves not only his confirmation, but likewiſe the limitation of his power, for before his Inauguration they made a league<note n="(e)" place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> with him; that is, obliged him by compact to the performance of ſuch conditions as they thought ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie for the ſecuring their Libertie. Nor is it leſſe remarkable, that when God gives di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections to his people concerning their government, he plainly leaves the Forme to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: for he ſaies not, when thou ſhalt have come into the land which the Lord thy God gives thee, <hi>Statues ſuper to Regem,</hi> But, <hi>Si</hi>
                  <note n="[f]" place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Dixeris ſtatuam.</hi> God ſaies not, thou ſhalt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point a King over thee, But if thou ſhalt ſay, I will appoint; leaving it to their choice whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they would ſay ſo or no. And it is plaine in that place that God gives the people the choice of their King, for he there inſtructs them whom they ſhal chooſe, <hi>Emedio fratrum tuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> one out of the midſt of thy brethren; much more might we ſay, if it were a leſſe mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Truth, that all juſt power of goverment is founded upon theſe two baſes, of Gods imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate command, or the Peoples conſent. And therefore whoſoever arrogates to himſelf that power, or any part of it, that cannot produce one of thoſe two titles, is not a Ruler, but an Invader, and thoſe that are ſubject to that power, are not governed, but opp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt.</p>
               <p>This being conſidered have not the people of England much reaſon to ask the Protector this Queſtion; <hi>Quis conſtunit te virum Principem &amp; judicem ſuper nos?</hi> Who made thee a Prince and a Judge over us? If God made thee, make it manifeſt to us. If the people, where did we meet to doe it? Who took our Subſcriptions? To whom deputed we our authority? And when and where did thoſe Deputies make the choice? Sure theſe interrogations are very naturall, and I beleeve would much trouble his Highnes his Councill, &amp; his Junto to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. In a word, that I may not tyre my reader (who will not want proofs for what I ſay, if he wants not memory;) If to change the goverment without the peoples conſent: If to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve their Repreſentatives by ſorce, and diſanull their Acts: If to give the name of the Peoples Repreſentatives to conſederates of his own, that he may eſtablish iniquitie by a law: If to take away mens lives out of all courſe of law, by certain Murtherers of his own ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, whom he names, <hi>A High Court of Iuſtice.</hi> If to decimate mens eſtates, and by
<pb facs="tcp:164183:3"/>his owne power to impoſe upon the people what Taxes he pleaſes: And to maintaine all this by force of Armes: If I ſay all this does make a Tyrant, his owne impudence cannot denie but he is as compleate a one as ever hath been ſince there have been Societies of Men. He that hath done, &amp; does all this, is the perſon for whoſe preſervation the people of England muſt pray; but certainly if they doe, tis for the ſame Reaſon that the old woman of Syracuſe prayd for the long life of the Tyrant <hi>Dyoniſius,</hi> leaſt the Divel ſhould come next.</p>
               <p>Now if inſtead of Gods command or the peoples conſent his Highnes hath no other Title but force &amp; fraud, which is to want all Title: And if to violate all lawes &amp; propoſe none to Rule by, but thoſe of his owne will, Be to exerciſe that Tyranie he hath uſurp't, and to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke his Adminiſtration conformable to his clayme: Then the firſt Queſtion we propoſed is a Queſtion no Longer.</p>
               <p>But before wee come to the ſecond, being thnigs are more Eaſily perceived &amp; found by the deſcription of theire <hi>Exteriour Accidents, &amp; Qualities,</hi> then the defining theire Eſſences: It will not be Amiſſe to ſee, whether his Highnes hath not as well the outward Markes &amp; Characters by which Tyrants are Known as he hath theire <hi>Nature &amp; Eſſentiall</hi> properties: Whether he hath not the Skynne of the Lyon &amp; Tayle of the Fox, as well as he hath the Violence of the one &amp; Deceipt of the other. Now in this Delineation which I intend to make of a Tyrant, all the Lineaments, all the Colours, will be found ſo Naturally to correſpond with the life, that it cannot but be doubted, whether his Highnes be the Originall or the Coppy. Whether I have in drawing the Tyrant Repreſented him: or in Repreſenting him Expreſt a Tyrant. And therefore leaſt I ſhould be ſuſpected to deale un-ſinceerly with his Highnes and not to have Applyed <hi>Theſe</hi> follownig Characters, but made them, I ſhall not give you any of my owne Stamping but ſuch as I finde in Plato, <hi>Ariſtotle, Tacitus,</hi> &amp; his Highnes own <hi>Euangeliſt, Machiavell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Almoſt all Tyrants have beene firſt Captaines &amp; Generalls for the people:<note place="margin">The Markes of a Tyrant. Ariſt. pol. lib. <hi>5</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi> vid. mach. Diſcor. lib. <hi>1</hi> cap. <hi>40.</hi>
                  </note> under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of vindicating, or defending theire Liberties. <hi>Vt Imperium evertant Libertatem prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerunt; cum perverterunt, ipſam aggrediuntur;</hi> ſayes <hi>Tacitus</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">An lib. <hi>1.</hi> Idem alibi. Caterum liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas &amp; Specio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa nomina pra. texuntur, nec quiſquam a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunam ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium. &amp; De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina ionem, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>cupivil, ut non eadem iſta vocabula uſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>paret. Mach. Diſcors. l. <hi>2.</hi> c <hi>13.</hi>
                  </note> to ſubvert the preſent Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they pretend Liberty for the people, when the Goverment is downe, they then Invade that libertie them ſelves, this nedes no Application.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Tyrants accomplſhs their ends much more by fraud then force. Neither vertue nor force (ſayes Machiavell)<note n="(b)" place="margin">il princ. cap. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> are ſo neceſſary, to that purpoſe as <hi>una Aſtutia fortunata,</hi> a Luckie craft: which ſayes he<note n="(c)" place="margin">Diſc. lib. <hi>2.</hi> c <hi>13.</hi>
                  </note> without force hath been often found ſufficient, but never force without that. And in another place<note n="(d)" place="margin">Princ. c. <hi>18.</hi>
                  </note> he tels us their way is <hi>Aggirare I cervelli de gli huo. mini con Aſtutia &amp;c.</hi> With cunning plauſible pretences to impoſe upon mens underſtandings &amp; in the end they maſter thoſe that had ſo little wit as to rely upon their faith &amp; integritie.</p>
               <p>Tis but unneceſſary to ſay, that had not his Highnes had a faculty to be fluent in his teares, and eloquent in his execrations: Had he not had ſpungie eyes, and a ſupple conſcience; and beſides to doe with a people of great faith, but little wit: his courage and the reſt of his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall uertues, with the help of his Janizaties, had never been able ſo ſarr to advance him out of the reach of juſtice, that we ſhould have need to call for any other hand to remove him, but that of the Hangman.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They abaſe all excellent perſons and rid out of the way all that have noble mindes <hi>Et Terrae filios extollunt;</hi> and advance Sons of the Earth.</p>
               <p>To put A riſtotle into other words, they purge both Parliament and army til they leave few or none there, that have ether honour or conſcience, ether witt, <hi>Intereſt,</hi> or Courage to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe theire deſignes. And in theſe Purgations (Sayth Plato) (e) Tyrants doe quite contrary to Phyſitians; for they purge us of our humours, but Tyrants of our Spirits.</p>
               <p n="4">4. They dare ſuffer noe Aſſemblies. Not ſomuch as Horſe-races.</p>
               <p n="5">5. In all places they have theyre Spies &amp; Dilators, that is, they have theire Fleetwoods, their Broughalls, their St. John's (beſides innumerable ſinalle ſpyes) to appeare diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented &amp; not to ſide with them; that under that disguiſe they may get truſt, and make diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers. They likewiſe have their Emiſſaties to ſend with forged letters.<note place="margin">Ariſt Pub. l. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. Plato de Repub. l. <hi>8.</hi> Ibid.</note> If any doubt this let him ſend to Major general Browne, and he will Satisfie Him.</p>
               <p n="6">6. They Stirre not without a guarde, nor his Highnes without his life guarde.</p>
               <p n="7">7. They impoveriſh the people, that they may want the power, if they have the will to attempt any thing againſt them. His Highnes way is by taxes, Exciſe, Decimations &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="8">8. They make warre to divert and buſie the people:<note place="margin">Ariſt. Ibid. Ariſt. Ibid. Id Ibid. &amp; Plato de Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> And beſides to have a pretence to rayſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oneys and to make new Leavies, if they either diſtruſt their old forces or thinke them not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fficient. The warre with Spain ſerveth his Highnes to this purpoſe, and upon noe other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> was it began at firſt, or is ſtill continued.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:164183:4"/>lawfull, and furniſh him with Title: his Highnes will likewiſe be then content to underſtand Scripture in their favour &amp; furniſh them with Tithes.</p>
               <p n="10">10.<note place="margin">Michiev. Pr. cap. <hi>19.</hi> Machiavel ads And do grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full things the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. But that I omit; for I really am un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provided of an inſtance for his Highnes, for I have not yet heard of any good he hath done himſelf. <hi>Ariſt. Ibid.</hi> Plato de Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub. lib. <hi>8.</hi> Id. &amp; Plut. paſſim.</note> Things that are odious and diſtaſtfull they make others executioners of, and when the people are diſcontented, they appeaſe them with Sacrifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing thoſe Miniſters they imploy: I leave it to his Highnes his Major generalls to ruminate a little upon this point.</p>
               <p n="11">11. In all things they pretend to be wonderfull carefull of the Publique: to give generall accompts of the money they receive, which they pretend to be leavied for the maintenance of the State, and the proſecuting of the warr. His Highnes made an excellent Comment upon this place of Ariſtotle in his ſpeech to this Parlement.</p>
               <p n="12">12. All things ſet aſide for Religious uſes they ſet to ſale; that while thoſe things laſt, they may exact the leſſe of the people. The Cavaliers would interpret this of the Dean and Chapters Lands.</p>
               <p n="13">13. They pretend inſpirations from Gods, and reſponces from Oracles to Authoriſe what they doe, his Highnes hath been ever an Enthuſiaſt. And as Hugh Capet, in taking the Crown, pretended to be admoniſh't to it in a dreame by St. Valery, and St. Richard: ſo I beleeve will his Highnes doe the ſame, at the inſtigation of St. Henry and St. Richard his two Sonnes.</p>
               <p n="14">14. Laſtly, Above all things they pretend a love to God and Religion. This Ariſtotle cals <hi>Artuae Tyrannic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rae potiſſimam;</hi> the ſureſt and beſt of all the Artes of Tyrants, and we al know his Highnes hath found it ſo by experience.<note place="margin">Hiſtor. of Franc. Ibid. lib. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> He hath found indeed that in godlineſſe there is great gain; and that preaching and praying, well managed; will obtain other kingdomes as well as that of Heaven. His indeed have been pious Armes, for he hath conquered moſt by thoſe of the Church, by prayers and<note n="(a)" place="margin">Preces &amp; Lacry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae ſunt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma Eccleſiae.</note> teares. But the truth is, were it nor for our honour to be governed by one that can manage both the ſpirituall and temporall ſword, and Roman like, to have our Emperour our High Prieſt: We might have had preaching at a much cheaper rate, and it would have coſt us but our Tithes, which now coſts us all.</p>
               <p>Other markes and rules there are mentioned by Ariſtotle to know Tyrants by: but they being unſuitable to his Hig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nes Actions, and impracticable by his temper, I inſiſt not on them. As among other things<note n="(b)" place="margin">Pol. lib. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> Ariſtotle would not have a Tyrant inſolent in his beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, nor ſtrike people But his Highnes is naturally chollerique, &amp; moſt call men Rogues, and goe to Cuffes. At laſt he concludes he ſhould ſo faſhion his manners, as neither to be really good, nor abſolutely bad, but half one, half tother. Now this half good is too great a proportion for his Highnes, and much more then his temper will beare.</p>
               <p>But to ſpeak truths more ſeriouſly, and to conclude this firſt queſtion. Certainly what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver theſe characters make any man, it cannot be denied but his Highnes is, and then if he be not a Tyrant, we muſt confeſſe we have no definition nor deſcription of a Tyrant left us; &amp; may well imagine there is no ſuch thing in nature, and that tis onely a notion and a name. But if there be ſuch a Beaſt, and we do at all believe what we ſee and feel; let us now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, according to the method we propoſed, whether this be a Beaſt of game that we are to give law to, or a Beaſt of Prey to deſtroy with all meanes are allowable and fair?</p>
               <p>In deciding this queſtion authours very much differ,<note place="margin">Whether it be lawful to kil a Tyrant?.</note> as farr as at concerns ſupteame Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, who degenerate into Tyrants. Some think they are to be born with as bad<note n="(c)" place="margin">Ames Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentem ſi a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quns eſt; ſi non, ſeras.</note> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents; and place them in the number of thoſe miſc. ieſs<note n="(d)" place="margin">Sicut ſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litatem, aut nimios imbres &amp;c. Tacit.</note> that have no other cure but our patience. Others think they may be queſtioned by that ſupreame law of the peoples ſafety; and that they are anſwerable to the peoples Repreſentatives for the bre cho their truſt. But none, of ſober ſenſe, makes private perſons judges of their actions; which were indeed to ſubvert all government. But on the other ſide, I find none, that have not been frighted or corrupted out of their reaſon, that have been ſo great enemies to common juſtice, and the Liberty of mankinde; as to give any kind of indemnity to a Uſurper, who can pretend no title, but that of being ſtronger; nor challenge the peoples obedience upon any other obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation but that of their neceſſity, &amp; fear. Such a perſon, as one out of all bounds of humane protection, all men make the Iſhmael,<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 16.12.</note> againſt whom is every mans hand, as his is againſt every man. To him they give no more ſecurity then Cain, his fellow-murtherer and oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour, promiſed to himſelf, to be deſtroyed by him that found him firſt.</p>
               <p>The reaſon why a Tyrants caſe is particular, &amp; why in that every man hath that vengance given him, which in other caſes is reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rved to God and the Magiſtrate, cannot be obſcure, if we rightly conſider what a Tyrant is, what his crimes are, and in what ſtate he ſtands with the Common wealth, and with every member of it. And certainly if we find him an enemy to al humane ſociety, and a ſubverter of all laws, and one that by the greatnes of his villanies, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of juſtice: we ſhall not at all think it ſtrongs if
<pb facs="tcp:164183:4"/>then he have no benefit from humane ſociety, no protection from the law, and if, in his caſe, juſtice diſpenſes with her formes. We are therefore to conſider that the end, for which men enter into ſocietie, is not barely to live, which they may doe diſperſt, as other Animals: but to live happily; and a Life anſwerable to the dignity and excellency of their kind. Out of Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, this happineſſe is not to be had, for ſingly we are impotent, and deſective, unable to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure thoſe things that are either of neceſſity, or ornament for our lives; and as unable to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſend and keep them when they are acquired. To Remedy theſe defects, we Aſſociate together that what we can neither enjoy nor keep, ſingly, by mutuall beneſits and aſſiſtances, one of another, We may be able to doe both. We cannot poſſibly accomplish theſe ends, if we ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit not our paſſions and appetites to the lawes of reaſon and juſtice. For the depravitie of mans will makes him as unfit to live in Societie, as his neceſſity makes him unable to live out of it. And if that perverſneſſe be not regulated by lawes, mens appetites to the ſame things; their avarice, their luſt, their ambition would quickly make Society as unſafe, or more, then Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude it ſelf, and we should aſſociate only to be nearer our miſerie and our ruine. That there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by which we accomplish the ends of a Sociable life, is our ſubjection, and ſubmiſſion to lawes, theſe are the Nerves and Sinews of every Society or Common-Wealth; Without which they muſt neceſſarily diſſolve and fall aſunder.<note place="margin">De Civit. Dei.</note> And indeed (as Auguſtine ſayes) thoſe Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties where law and juſtice is not, are not Common-Wealths or Kingdomes, but <hi>Magna Latro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinia,</hi> Great Confederacies of Thieves and Robbers. Thoſe therefore that ſubmit to no lavv are not to be reputed in the Society of mankind, which cannot conſiſt without a law. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Ariſtotle<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pol. lib. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> ſaith, Tyrannie is againſt the law of nature, that is, the law of humane So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, in which humane nature is preſerved. For this reaſon they deny a Tyrant to be <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem Civitatis;</hi> for every part is ſubject to the whole: and a Citizen (ſaies the ſame authour,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Lib. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> is he who is as well obliged to the duty of obeying, as he is capable of the power of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding. And indeed he does obey whilit he does command, that is, be obeys the lawes, which (ſaies Tully) <hi>Maciſtratibus praeſunt, ut Magiſtratus praeſunt Populo,</hi> are above the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, as the Magiſtrates are above the people. And therefore a Tyrant that ſubmits to no law; but his will and luſt are the law, by which he governs himſelf and others, is no Magiſtrate, no Citizen or member of any Society, but an Ulcer and a diſeaſe that detroyes it, and if it be rightly conſidered, a Common-wealth by falling into a Tyrannie al ſolutely looſes that name, and is actually an other thing: <hi>Non eſt civitas quae unius eſt viri</hi> (ſaies Sophocles) that which is one mans, is no city. For there is no longer King and People, or Parlement and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but thoſe names are changed (at leaſt their natures) into Maſters and Servants, Lord and Slaves: And <hi>Servorum non Civitas erit ſed magna Familia</hi> (ſaies Grotius)<note n="(c)" place="margin">de jur. bel. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> where all are Slaves, tis not a Citty but a great Family. And the truth is, we are all members of Whithall, and when our maſter pleaſeth, he May ſend for us thither, and there bore through our Eares at the door poſts. But to conclude, a Tyrant, as we have ſaid, being no part of a Common-wealth, nor ſubmitting to the laws of it, but making himſelf above al law: There is no reaſon he should have the protection that is due to a member of a Common-wealth, nor any defence from laws, that does acknowledge none. He is therefore in all reaſon to be reckoned in the number of thoſe Savage Beaſts, that full not with others into any heard: that have no other defence but their own ſtrength; making a prey of all thats weaker, and, by the ſame juſtice, being a prey to all thats ſtronger then themſelves.</p>
               <p>In the next place, let it be conſidered, that a Tyrant making himſelf above all law, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending his injuſtice by a ſtrength which no power of Magiſtrates is able to appoſe: he becoms above all punishment, above all other juſtice, then that he receives from the ſtroak of ſome generous hand. And certainly the ſafety of mankinde were but ill provided for, if there were no kind of juſtice to reach great villanies, but Tyrants should be <hi>Immanitate Scelerum tuti,</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured by the greatneſſe of their crimes. Our lawes would be then but Cobwebs indeed, made only to catch Flies; but not to hold Waſps or Hornets: And it might be then ſaid of all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths, what was ſaid of Athens, That there onely ſmall Theeves were hanged, but the great ones were free, and condemned the reſt. But he that will ſecure himſelf of all hands, muſt know he ſecures himſelf from none: He that flies juſtice in the Court, muſt expect to finde it in the ſtreet: &amp; he that goes armed againſt every man; armes every man againſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. <hi>Bellum eſt in eos, Qui judiciis Coerceri non poſſunt</hi> (ſaies Cicero) We have warr with thoſe againſt whom we can have no law. The ſame Authour, <hi>Cum duo ſint decertandi genera, &amp;c.</hi> There being two wayes of deciding differences, the one by judgement and Arbitration, the other by Force: the one proper to men, the other to beaſts. We muſt have recourſe to the latter, when the former cannot be obtained. And cerrainly by the law of nature,<note place="margin">Grot. de jur Bel. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ubi ceſſat Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m,</hi> when no juſtice can be had, every man may be his own Magiſtrate, and doe juſtice for
<pb facs="tcp:164183:5"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:164183:5"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:164183:6"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:164183:6"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:164183:7"/>himſelf.<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> For the law (ſaies Grotius) that forbids me to purſue my right but by a courſe of law: Certainly ſuppoſes, <hi>Vbi copia eſt Iudicii,</hi> where law and juſtice is to be had: otherwiſe that law were a defence for injuries, not one againſt them: and quite contrary to the nature of all lawes; would become the protection of the guilty againſt the innocent, not of the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent againſt the guilty.<note place="margin">Deut. <hi>17.</hi>
                  </note> Now as it is contrary to the laws of God and nature, that men, who are partial to themſelves, and therefore unjuſt to others, should be their own judges, where others are to be had: ſo is it as contrary to the law of nature, and the common ſafety of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, that when the law can have no place, men should be forbidden to repell force by force, and ſo be left without all defence &amp; remedie againſt injuries. God himſelf left not the ſlave without remedie againſt the cruell Maſter: And what Analogie can it hold with reaſon, that the ſlave that is but his Maſters mony; and but part of his Houshold-ſtuff, ſhould find re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe againſt the <hi>Injuries,</hi> and inſolencies of an imperious Maſter, and a free people, who have no ſuperiour but their God, should have none at all againſt the injuſtice and oppreſſion of a Barbarous Tyrant? And were not the incongruity fully as great, that the law of God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting every man to kil a thief, if he took him breaking open his houſe in the night: becauſe then it might be ſuppoſed he could not bring him to juſtice; But a Tyrant, that is the common Robber of mankinde, and whom no law can take hold on, his perſon should be, <hi>Sacroſanct, cui nihil Sacrum aut Sanctum,</hi> to whom nothing is Sacred, nothing Inviolable? But the vulger judge ridiculouſly like themſelves. The gliſter of things dazles their eyes, and they judge of them by their appearances; and the colours that are put on them. For what can be more ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd in nature, and contrary to all common ſence, then to call him thief and Kill him, that comes alone, or with a few to Robb me: And to call him Lord Protectour and obey him, that robbes me with Regiments and Troops?<note place="margin">Ex. <hi>21.</hi>
                  </note> As if to rove with two or three Ships were to be a Pirate, but with fifty an Admirall? But if it be the number of adherents only, not the cauſe, that makes the difference between a Robber and a Protectour: I wish that number were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined, that we might know where the Thief ends, and the Prince beginns. And be able to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguish between a Robbery and a Tax. But ſure no Engliſh man can be ignorant, that it is his Birth-right to be maſter of his own Eſtate; and that none can command any part of it but by his own grant and conſent, either made expreſly by himſelf, or Virtually by a Parliament. All other waies are meere Robberies in other names: <hi>Auferre, Trucidare, Rapere, falſis nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus imperium,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ex.</hi> 22.2.</note> 
                  <hi>atque ubi ſolitudinem faciunt, pacem apellant:</hi> To Robbe, to extort, to murder Tyrants falſly cald to Govern, and to make deſolation, they call to ſettle peace: in every aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſement we are Rob'd, the Exciſe is Robbery, the Cuſtoumes Robbery, &amp; without doubt, when ever us prudent, tis alwayes lawfull, to kill the thieves, whom we can bring to no other juſtice.<note place="margin">Tacit. in Vid. Agric.</note> And not onely lawfull, and to doe our ſelves right, but Glorious, and to deſerve of mankind, to free the World of that common robber, that univerſall Pirat, under whom, and for whom, the leſſer beaſts prey. This Firebrand I would have any way extinguisht: This Ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer I would have any hand to lance. And I cannot doubt but God wil ſuddenly ſanctifie ſome hand to doe it, and bring down that bloody and deceitfull man, who lives not onely to the miſery, but the infamie of our nation.</p>
               <p>I should have reaſon to be much leſſe confident of the juſtice of this opinion, if it were new, and only grounded upon Collections and Interpretations of my own. But herein if I am de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, I shall however have the excuſe to have been drawn into that errour, by the examples that are leſt us by the greateſt and moſt vertuous, and the opinions of the wiſeſt and graveſt men, that have leſt their memories to poſterity. Out of the great plenty of confirmations I could bring for this opinion, from examples and authorities; I shall ſelect a very few; for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt truths have not need of thoſe ſupports; and I have as little minde to tire my ſelf as my Reader.<note place="margin">de in Bel: l b <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt therefore a Uſurper that by only force poſſeſeth himſelf of government, and by force onely keeps it, is yet in the State of warr with every man, ſaies the learned Grotius: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore every thing is lawfull againſt him, that is lawfull againſt an open enemy, whom every private man hath a right to kill.<note place="margin">Luc. l b. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Hoſtis hoſtem occidere volui</hi> ſaies Scaevola to Porſena; when he was taken, after he had failed in his attempt to kill him; I am an enemy and an enemy I would have kil'd; which every man hath a right to doe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Contra publicos hoſtes, &amp; Majeſtatis Reos, omnis homo miles eſt</hi> (ſayes <hi>Tertullian,</hi>) Againſt common enemies, and thoſe that are Traitors to the common wealth, every man is a Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier. This opinion the moſt Celebrated nations have approved both by their laws &amp; practiſes. The Grecians (as Zeaophon tells us) who ſuffered not Murderers to come into their Templs, in thoſe very Temples they erected Statutes to thoſe that kil'd Tyrants, thinking it fit to place their deliverers amongſt their Gods. Cicero was an eye witneſſe of the honours that were
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:164183:7"/>done ſuch men, <hi>Graeci hominet &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro milont</note> The Greekes (ſaieth he) attribute the honours of the Gods to thoſe that kild Tyrants: What have I ſeen in Athens and Other Cities of Greece! What Religion Paid to ſuch men! What ſongs! What Elogies!<note place="margin">Plut. in Solon.</note> By which they are Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Immortallity, and almoſt Deified! In Athens, by Solons Law, Death was not only decree'd for the Tyrant that oppreſt the State, but for all thoſe that tooke any Charge,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Let his Highnes junto mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket this. De Repub. lib <hi>8.</hi> In Public.</note> or did beate any office while the Tyranny remained. And Plato tells us the ordinary Courſe they tooke with Tyrants in Greece. If (ſayes he) the Tyrant can not be expuls't by Accuſing him to the Cittizens; then by ſecret practiſes they diſpatch him.</p>
               <p>Amongſt the Romans the Valerean law was, <hi>ſi quis injuſſu populi &amp;c.</hi> Who ſoever took Magiſtracy upon him, without the command of the people it was lawfull for any man to kill him. Plutarch makes this law more Severe, <hi>ut Injudicatum occidere eum liceret. Qui Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatum concupiſceret.</hi> That it was lawfull by that law, before any judgment paſt, to kill him that but Aſpired to Tyranny. Likewiſe the Conſular law which was made after the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of the Tyranny of the Decemvirate, made it lawfull to kill any man that went about to Create Magiſtrates, <hi>ſine Provocatione &amp;c.</hi> Without reference and Appeal to the people. By theſe lawes and Innumerable teſtimonies of Authours, it appeares; that the Romans, with the reſt of theyre Philoſophy, had learned from the Grecians what was the naturall Remedie againſt a lyrant: nor did they honour theſe leſſe that durſt apply it. Who as Polybius Sayes (Speaking of Conſpiracies againſt Tyrants) were not,<note place="margin">Hiſt. lib. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Deterrimi Civium, ſed Generoſiſiimi Quique, &amp; Maximi Auimi;</hi> not the worſt and meaneſt of the Cittizens, but the moſt Generous, and theſe of Greateſt vertue. Soe were moſt of theſe that conſpired againſt Julius Caeſar. He himſelf thought Brutus worthy to ſucceed him in the Empire of the world: And Cicero, who had the title of <hi>Pater Patriae;</hi> if he were not conſcious of the deſigne, Yet he at leaſt affected the honour of being thought ſoe. <hi>Quae enim Res unquam &amp;c.</hi> What Act (ſayes he) o Jupiter more glorious!<note place="margin">Philip. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> more worthy of Eternall memorie, hath beene done not only in this Citty, but in the whole world! In this deſigne, as the Troyan Horſe, I willingly ſuffer my ſelf to be Included with the Princes. In the ſame place he tells us what all vertuous Romans thought of the fact aſwell as he. <hi>Omnes Boni, Quantum in ipſis fuit, Caeſarem occiderunt: aliis conſilium: aliis animus: aliis occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio defuit, Voluntas nemini,</hi> All Good men (Saith he) as much as lay in them killed Caeſat: Some wanted Capacity: ſome Courage: Others opportunity: But none the will to doe it. But yet we have not declared the extent of theire ſeverity againſt a Tyrant. They ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed him to fraud, as well as force, and left him no ſecurity in Oathes, and compacts: that neither law nor Religion might defend him, that violated Both. <hi>Cum Tyranno Romanis nulla fides, nulla jurisjurandi Religio,</hi> Saith Brutus in Appian:<note place="margin">Appian. lib. <hi>7.</hi> de Benef.</note> with a Tyrant the Romans thinke no faith to be kept, obſerve no Religion of an Oath. Seneca gives the Reaſon; <hi>Quia quicquid erat, quo mihi cohaereret &amp;c.</hi> For what ever there was of mutuall obligation betwixt us; his deſtroying the lawes of humane ſociety, hath diſſolud:<note place="margin">Sin.</note> ſoe theſe that thought, that there was in hoſtem nefas, that a villany might be committed againſt an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie: theſe that profes't, <hi>non minus juſte quam fortiter arma gerere,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Id.</note> to manage theire armes with juſtice as well as Courage: theſe that thought faith was to be kept even with the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidious,<note place="margin">Saul of</note> 
                  <note n="(b)" place="margin">Regulus Qui longum ſemper ſame &amp;c. Senec. in exerc. <hi>4.7.</hi> Mich. Ephes ad <hi>5.</hi> Nich.</note> yet they thought a Tyrant Could receiue no injuſtice, but to be let live; and that the moſt lawfull way to deſtroy him was the Readieſt. No matter wether by force or fraud; for againſt Beaſts of Prey, men uſe the toyle and the net as well as the ſpeare and the lance. But ſoe great was theire deteſtation of a Tyrant that it made ſome take theire opinions from theire paſſions; and vent things which they could but ill juſtifie to theire morality they thought a Tyrant had ſoe abſolutety forfeited all title to humanity, and all kind of Protection they could give him or his: that they left his wife without any other Guard for her chaſtity but age and deformity; and thought it not adultery what was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted with her. Many mote teſtimonies might I bring; for 'tis harder to make choice then to find plenty. But I ſhall conclude with Authorities that are much more Authentique; and examples we may much more ſately Imitate.</p>
               <p>The law of God it ſelf decree'd Certaine<note n="(c)" place="margin">Vtique morietur vir ille Deut. <hi>17.12.</hi>
                  </note> death to that man that would doe preſumptuously, and ſubmit to no Deciſion of Juſtice. Who can Read this and thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke a Tyrant ought to live? But Certainly neither that, nor any other law were to any effect, if there were no way to put it in execution. But in a Tyrants Caſe Proceſſe and Citation have no place, and if we will only have Formall Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies againſt him, we ave ſure to have none. Theres' ſmall hopes of Juſtice where the Malefactour hath a power to condemn the Judge.
<pb facs="tcp:164183:8"/>All remedie therfore againſt a Tyrant is Ehuds dagger, without which all our lawes were fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, and we helpleſſe. This is that high Court of juſtice where Moſes brought the Egyptian: whether Ehud brought Eglon: Samſon the Phililtins: Samuel Agag: and Jehoiada the she Tyrant Athaliah.</p>
               <p>Let us a little conſider in particular theſe ſeverall examples, and ſee whether they may be proportioned to our purpoſe.</p>
               <p>Firſt as to the caſe of Moſes and the Egiptian:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ex.</hi> 2.11.12</note> certainly every Englishman hath as much call as Moſes, and more cauſe then he, to ſlay this Egiptian that is alwayes laying on burdens and alwayes ſmiting both our brethren and our ſelves. For as to his call, he had no other that we read of, but the neceſſity his brother ſtood in of his help. He look't on his brethrens bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, and ſeeing an Egiptian ſmiting an Hebrew, knowing he was out of the reach of all other kind of juſtice, he ſlew him. Certainly this was and is as lawfull for any man to doe, as it was for Moſes, who was then but a private man, and had no authority for what he did, but what the law of nature gives every man; to oppoſe force to force, and to make juſtice where he findes none. As to the cauſe of that action, we have much more to ſay then Moſes had: He ſaw one Hebrew ſmitten, we many Englishmen murderd; He ſaw his brethrens burdens, and their blowes, we our brethrens burdens, impriſonments and deaths. Now ſure if it were lawfull for Moſes to kill that Egiptian that oppreſt one man, being there was no way to procure an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary courſe of juſtice agains him: It cannot be but abſurd to think it unlawfull to kill him<note n="(a)" place="margin">vid. Et. Governador Chriſtiano. c. <hi>8.</hi> p <hi>40.</hi> Qualquiera ciudadano me de repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter la fuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta &amp;c.</note> that oppreſſes a whole nation, and one that juſtice as little reaches as it defends.</p>
               <p>The example of Ehud shews us the naturall and almoſt the only remedie againſt a Tyrant, and the way to free an oppreſt people from the ſlavery of an inſulting Moabite, tis done by prayers and teares, with the help of a Dagger, by <hi>(b)</hi> crying to the Lord, and the left hand of an Ehud. Devotion and action goe wel together; for beleeve it, a Tyrant is not of that kinde of Devill that is to be caſt out by only faſting and prayer: And here the Scripture shews us what the Lord thought a fit meſſage to ſend a Tyrant from himſelf:<note place="margin">Iudg. c. <hi>3.</hi> v. <hi>11.19.20.</hi> v. <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> A Dagger of a cubit in his Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and every worthy man that deſires to be an Ehud, a deliverer of his Countrie, will ſtrive to be the meſſenger.</p>
               <p>We may here likewiſe obſerve in this and many places of judges, that when the Iſraelites fel to Idolatry,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>v.</hi> 20.</note> which of all Siunes certainly is one of the greateſt: God Allrighty to proportion the punishment and the offence, ſtill delivered them into the hands of Tyrants; which ſure is one of the greateſt of all plagues.</p>
               <p>In the ſtory of Samſon tis manifeſt,<note place="margin">Iudg. <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> that the denying him his wife, and after the burning her and her father, which though they were great, yet were but private injuries, he took for ſufficient grounds to make warre upon the Philiſtians, being himſelf but a private man, and not onely not aſſiſted, but oppoſed (a) by his ſervile countrey men. He knew what the law of nature allowed him; where other lawes have no place, and thought it a ſufficient juſtification for ſmiting the Philiſtins hip and thigh to anſwer for himſelf,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>v.</hi> 11.</note> that as they did unto him, ſo had be done unto them.</p>
               <p>Now that which was lawfull for Samſon to doe againſt many oppreſſours, why is it unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for us to doe againſt one? are our injuries leſſe? out Friends and Relations are daily mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered before our faces. Have we otherwayes for reparation? let them be named and I am ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenc'd. But if we have none, the fire-brands, or the jawbone, the firſt weapons our juſt fury can lay hold on, may certainly be lawfully employed againſt that uncircumciſed Philiſtin. that oppreſſes us.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>v.</hi> 14.</note> We have too the oppoſition and diſcouragements that Samſon had, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore have the more need of his courage &amp; reſolution. As he had the men of Judah, ſo we have the men of Levi, crying to us out of the Pulpit, as from the top of the Rock Etam, know you not that the Philiſtin is a Ruler over you? The truth is, they would fain make him ſo, &amp; bind us with Samſon in new cordes, but we hope they will become as Flax, and that they will ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther looſe from our hands, or we shall have the courage to cut them.</p>
               <p>Upon the ſame grounds of Retatiation did Samuel doe juſtice with his own hand upon the Tyrant Agag.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.33.</note> As thy ſword (ſaies the Prophet) hath made Women childleſſe, ſo shall thy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be childleſſe amongſt Women, nor is there any law more naturall and more juſt.</p>
               <p>How many mothers has our Agag, for his own ambition, made childleſſe? how many chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren Fatherleſſe? how many have this reaſon to hew this Amalakite in pieces before the Lord? And let his own relations, and all theirs that are confederates with him, beware, leaſt men come at laſt to revenge their own relations in them.<note place="margin">in Diſcors.</note> They make many a woman husban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, many a father childleſſe. Their wives may come at laſt to know what tis to want a huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and themſelves to looſe their children. Let them remember what their great Apoſtle Machiavell tells them; that in conteſtations for the preſerving their liberty, people many
<pb facs="tcp:164183:8"/>times uſe moderation; but when they come to vindicate it, their rigour exceeds all meane, like beaſts that have been kept up, &amp; are afterwards let looſe, they alwayes are more fierce &amp; cruell.</p>
               <p>To conclude with the example Jehoiada hath left us.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Kings. cap.</hi> 11. 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 23</note> Six yeares he hid the right Heir of the Crown in the houſe of the Lord, and without all doubt, amongſt the reſt of Gods ſervices there he was all that time contriving the deſtruction of the Tyrant, that had aſpired to the Crown by the deſtruction of thoſe that had the right to it. Jehoiada had no pretence to authorice this action; but the equity &amp; Juſtice of the act it ſelf. He pretended no immediate command from God for what he did, nor any authority from the Sanedrym, &amp; therefore any man might have done what Jehoiada did as lawfully, that could have done it as effectually as he. Now what ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation was given to Athaliah, what appearance was she cal'd to before any court of juſtice:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chron.</hi> 23.14.</note> her fact was her triall, she was without any expoſtulation taken forth of the Ranges and onley let live till she got out of the Temple, that that Holy place might not be defiled by the blood of a Tyrant, which was fitter to be shed on a dung-hill, and ſo they ſlew her at the Horſ-gate. And by the Kings houſe, the very White-hall, where she had cauſed the Blood-Royall to be ſpilt, &amp; which her ſelf had ſo long anjuſtly poſſeſt, there by Providence did she receive her punishment where she had acted ſo great a part of her crimes. How the people approved of this Glorious action of de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>roying a Tyrant, this Chapter tels us at the laſt verſe. And all the people of the land rejoyced, and the City was quiet, after that they had ſlain Athalian with the ſword.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 23.14. 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 24.16.</note> And that it may appeare they no leſſe honoured the Authours of ſuch actions, then other Nations did; as in his lifetime they obeyed Jehoiada as a King, ſo after his death, for the good he had done in Iſrael (ſaith the Scripture) they likewiſe buried him amongſt the Kings.</p>
               <p>I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> conclude this ſtory without obſerving that Jehoiada commanded,<note place="margin">Mr. Sirder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>combs judge &amp; jury may likewiſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of this point.</note> that whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver followed Athaliah should be put to death Letting us ſee what they deſerve that are Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates with Tyrants and will ſide with them, and but appear to defend them, or allow them, his Highnes his Counſell, his Junto, and the Agaes of his Janizaries, may, if they, leaſe, take notice of this and repent, leaſt they likewiſe perish. And likewiſe his Highnes his Chaplains, and Tryers who are to admit none into the miniſtry that will preach liberty with the Goſpell; may if they think fit, obſerve, that with the Tyrant ſell Mattan the Prieſt of Baal. And indeed none but Baals prie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s will preach for Tyrants. And certainly thoſe prieſts that Sacrifice to out Baal, our Idol of a Magiſtrate, deſerves as wel to be hang'd before their Pulpits,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 23.17.</note> as ever Matian did to fall before his Altars.</p>
               <p>I should think now I had ſaid much more then enough to the ſecond queſtion, &amp; should com to the third and laſt I propoſed in my method: but I meet with two objections lying in my way. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>1</label> The firſt is, That theſe examples out of Scripture are of men that were Inſpired of God, and that therefore they had that call and authority for their actions, which we cannot pretend to, ſo that it would be unſafe for us to draw their actions into examples, except we had like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe their juſtifications to alledg.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>2</label> The other objection is, that there being now no oppoſition made to the goverment of his Highnes, that the people following their callings &amp; traffique at home and abroad, making uſe of the laws, &amp; appealing to his Highnes courts of juſtice: That all this argues the peoples tacit conſent to the Goverment; and that therefore now tis to be reputed lawfull, and the peoples obedience voluntary.<note place="margin">Iob. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>To the firſt I anſwer with learned Milton, that if God commanded theſe things, tis a ſigne they were lawfull and are commendable. But ſecondly, as I obſerved in the relations of the examples themſelves; Neither Samſon nor Samuel alledged any other cauſe or reaſon for what they did, but retaliation, and the apparent juſtice of the actions themſelves. Nor had God appeared to Moſes in the Buſh when he ſlew the Egyptian; nor did Jehoiada alleadg any Propheticall authority or other call to doe what he did, but that common call which all men have, to doe all actions of juſtice that are within their power, when the ordinary courſe of juſtice ceaſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>2</label> To the ſecond my anſwer is, that if commerce and pleadings were enough to Argue the peoples conſent, &amp; give Tyrannie the name of Goverment, there was never yet any Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of many weeks ſtanding in this world. Certainly, we then extreemly wrong Caligula &amp; Nero in calling them Tyrants, and they were rebells that conſpired againſt them; except wee will beleeve, that all the while they reign'd, that in Rome they kept their ſhops ſhut, &amp; ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned not their Temples, or their Courts. We are likewiſe with no leſſe abſurdity, to imagine that the whole eighteen yeares time which Iſrael ſerved Eglon, &amp; ſix yeares that Athaliah reigned, that the Iſraelits quite deſiſted from traffique, pleadings &amp; all publique acts: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Ehud and Jehoiada were both Traitors, the one for killing his king, the other his queen.<note place="margin">Third Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Having ſhewed what a Tyrant is, his marks and practiſes: I can ſcarce perſwade my ſelf to
<pb facs="tcp:164183:9"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> proove of Advantage to the Common wealth or not? for methinkes tis to enquire whether tis better the man die or the Impoſtume be lanc't, or the Gangragen'd limbe be cut off? But yet there be ſome whoſe Cowardice &amp; Avarice furniſh them with ſome Arguments to the contrary; and they would fayne make the world beleeve, that to be baſe &amp; degenerate, is to be Cautious &amp; prudent: and what is in truth a ſervile feare, they falſely call a Chriſtian pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience. It will not be therfore a miſſe to make appear that there is indeed that neceſſity, which we think there is, of ſaving the vineyard of the Common wealth if poſſible, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying the wilde boar that is broke into it. We have already ſhewed that it is lawful, &amp; now we ſhal ſee whether it is expedient. Firſt I hae already tould you that, to be under a Tyrant is not to be a common wealth; but a great Family, conſiſting of maſter &amp; Slaves. <hi>Vir bone ſervo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum nulla eſt uſquam civitas</hi> ſayes an old Poet a nember of Slaves makes not a Citty. So that whilſt this Monſter lives wee are not members of a common wealth, but only his living tooles &amp; Inſtruments, which he may employ to what uſe he pleaſes. <hi>Servi tua eſt fortuna Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio ad te nihil</hi> ſayes an other; thy condition is a ſlaves; thou art not to enquire a Reaſon, not muſt wee think we can continue long in the condition of ſlaves, and not degenerate into the habits &amp; temper that is naturall to that condition: our mindes will grow low with our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, &amp; by benig accouſtumed to live like ſlaves, we ſhall become unfitt to be any thing Elſe <hi>Etiam fera animalia ſi clauſa teneas virtutis obliviſcuntur</hi> ſayes Tacitus<note n="(a)" place="margin">Hiſt. lib. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> the fierceſt creatures by long conſtraint, looſe theire courage. And ſayes Sr. Francis Bacon, the bleſſing of Iſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>char &amp; that of Judah falls not upon one people, to be Aſſes crouching under Burdens, &amp; to have the Spirit of Lyons. And with theyre courage tis no wonder <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> they looſe theire for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune as the Effect with the cauſe, and Act as Ignominiously abroad, as they ſuffer at home. Tis Machiavells<note n="(b)" place="margin">Diſcors lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>24.</hi>
                  </note> obſervation that the Romane Armies that were all wayes victorious under confulls, All the while they were under the ſlavery of the Decemviri never proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. And certainely people have Reaſon to fight but faintly where they are to gaine the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory againſt themſelves; when every ſucceſſe ſhall be a confirmation of theire ſlavery, and a new link to their chaine.</p>
               <p>But we ſhall not only looſe out Courage which is a uſeleſſe &amp; an unſafe vertu under a Tyrant, but by degrees we ſhall, after the example of our Maſter, All turne perfidious, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull Irreligious, flatterers, and what ever elſe is villanous and Infamous in Mankind. See but to what a degree we are come to already: can there any Oath be founde ſo fortifyed by all Religious Tyes; which we eaſily ſinde not a Diſtinction to breake, when eyther pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitt or Danger perſwades us to it? Doe we Remember any Engagements; or if we doe, have we any ſhame to breake them? Can any Man think with patience upon what we have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes't, when he ſees what wee vildly doe, and Tamely Suffer? what have we of nobillity among'ſt us but the name; the luxurie &amp; the vices of It? poore wretches theſe that now carry that title, are ſo farre from having any of the vertues, that ſhould grace and indeed give them theire titles,<note place="margin">Docter Loc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker Docter Owen Mr. lenkins &amp;c.</note> that they have not ſo much as the generous vices that attend great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, they have loſt all Ambition &amp; Indignation. As for our Miniſters; what have they, or indeed deſire they, of theire Calling, but the Tythes? How doe theſe horrid prevaricators ſearch for diſtinctions to peece contrary Oathes? How doe they Rake Scriptures for flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries? And Impudently Apply them to his monſtrous Highnes? what is the Citty but a Great Tame Beaſt, that eates &amp; Carries &amp; cares not who Rides it? whats the thing cal'd a Parlement but a Mock? Compoſed of a people that are only ſuffered to ſitt there becauſe they are knowne to have no verute, After the Exclution of all others that were but ſuſpected to have Any? What are they but pimpes of Tyranny, who are only Imployed to draw In the people to proſtitut theyre Liberty? What will not the army fight for? what will they not fight againſt! What are they but Janizaries, ſlaves themſelves; and making all others ſo? what are the people in Generall but Knaues, Fooles, &amp; Cowards; principled for Eaſe, vice &amp; Slavery? This is our temper, this Tyranny hath brought us to already; and if it continus, the little vertue that is yet left to ſtocke the Nation,<note place="margin">Diſc. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> muſt totally extinguish, and then his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes hath compleated his worke of Reformation. And the trueth is till then his Highnes can not be ſecure. He must not endure vertue, for that will not endure him. He that will maintay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Tyranny muſt kill Brutus ſayes Machiavell. A Tyrant ſayes Plato <hi>(c)</hi> muſt diſpatch all vertuous perſons or he can not be ſafe<note n="(ſ)" place="margin">de Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub. lib. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> ſo that he is brought to that un happy neceſſity, eyther to live amongſt Baſe &amp; wicked perſons, or not to live at all.</p>
               <p>Nor muſt we expect any Cure from our patience <hi>Inganno ſi gli huomini,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Diſc. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> ſayes Machiavell <hi>(a) credendo con la humilit à vincere la ſuperbia.</hi> Men deceive themſelves that think t0
<pb facs="tcp:164183:9"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> weak, tis in the winter of his fortune when this Serpent bites not: we muſt not therefore ſuffer our ſelves to be couzened with hopes of his amendment: for <hi>Nemo unquam</hi>
                  <note n="(d)" place="margin">Tacit. Hiſt. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Imperium flagitio quaeſitum bonis artibus exercuit;</hi> never did any man manage the Goverment with juſtice that got it by villany. The longer the Tyrant lives the more the Tirannicall humour encreaſes in him, ſaies Plato,<note n="(e)" place="margin">de Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub. lib.</note> like thoſe beaſts that grow more curſt as they grow old. New occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions daily happen, that neceſſitate them to new miſchiefs, and he muſt defend one villanie with another.</p>
               <p>But ſuppoſe the contrarie of all this, and that his Highnes were <hi>vi Domina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis convulſus, &amp; mutatus,</hi> changed to the better by great fortune (of which he yet gives no ſymptomes) what notwithſtanding could be more miſerable then to have no other ſecurity for our libertie, no other law for our ſaftie, then the will of a man, though the moſt juſt living?<note place="margin">Cic. Phil. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> we have all our beaſt within us, and whoſoever (ſayes Ariſtotle)<note n="(f)" place="margin">Pol. lib. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> is Governed by a man without a law, is governed by a man and by a beaſt. <hi>Etiam ſi non ſit moleſtus</hi> (a) <hi>Dominus; tamen eſt miſerrimum poſſe ſi velit,</hi> ſaies Tully, Though a maſter does not Tyrannize yet tis a moſt miſerable thing that tis in his power to do ſo if he will. If he be good, ſo was Nero for five yeares, and how shall we be ſecure that he will not change? Beſides the power that is allowed to a good man, we may be ſure will be claimed and taken by an ill. And therefore it hath been the couſtume of good princes<note n="(b)" place="margin">Lycur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus. Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pomp. plut. in Lycurg.</note> to abridge their own power, it may be diſtruſting themſelves, but certainly fearing their Succeſſors, to the chance of whoſe being vertuous; they would not hazard the welfare of their people. An unlimited power ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is to be truſted to none, which if it does not find a Tyrant, commonly makes one: or if one uſes it modeſtly tis no argument that others will, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Auguſtus Caeſar muſt have no greater power given him, then you would have Tiberius take. And (c) Ciceroes moderation is to be truſted with a conſideration, that there are others to be conſuls as well as he.<note place="margin">Vid Orat. Caeſaris in Salluſt. conſp. cat.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But before I preſſe this buſineſſe farther, if it needs be any farther preſt, that we should indeavour to reſcue the honour, the vertue and liberty of our nation I shall anſwer to ſome few objections that have occurred to me. This I shall doe very briefly.</p>
               <p>Some I find of a ſtrange opinion, that it were a generous and a noble action to kill his Highnes in the field; but to doe it privately they think it unlawfull, but know not why. As if it were not generous to apprehend a thief till his ſword were drawn and he in a poſture to defend himſelf and kill me. But theſe people do not conſider that whoſoever is poſleſt of power any time, wilbe ſure to ingage ſo many either in guilt or profit, or both, that to goe about to throw him out by open force, will very much hazard the totall ruine of the Common-Wealth. A Tyrant is a Devill that teares the body in the exorciſing,<note place="margin">Sueton. in vit. Caleg.</note> &amp; they are all of Caligulas temper, that if they could, they would have the whole frame of Nature fall with them. Tis an opinion that deſerves no other refutation then the manifeſt abſurdity of it ſelf; that it should be lawfull for me to deſtroy a Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ant with hazard, blood, and confuſion, but not without.</p>
               <p>An other objection and more common is the feare of what may ſucceed if his Highneſſe were removed, one would think the World were bewitched.
<pb facs="tcp:164183:10"/>I am fallen into a ditch where I shall certainly perish if I lie, but I refuſe to be helpt out for fear of falling into another, I ſuffer a certain miſerie for feare of a contingent one, &amp; let the diſeaſe kill me becauſe there is hazard in the cure. Is not this that ridiculous policie, <hi>Ne moriare, mori.</hi> To die for feare of dying. Sure tis frenzie not to deſire a change when we are ſure we cannot be worſe. <hi>Et non incurrere in pericula, ubi quies centi paria metnuntur,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Seneca.</note> and not then to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard, when the danger and the miſchiefs are the ſame in lying ſtill.</p>
               <p>Hitherto I have ſpoken in generall to all Englishmen, now I adreſſe my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe particularly to thoſe that certainly beſt deſerve that name, our ſelves, that have fought, however unfortunately, for our Liberties under this Tyrant; and in the end couzened by his oathes, and teares, have purchaſed nothing but our ſlavery with the price of our blood. To us particularly it belongs to bring this Monſter to juſtice, whom he hath made the inſtruments of his Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lany, and sharers in the Curſe and Deteſtation that is due to himſelf from all good men. Others only have their Liberty to vindicate, we our Liberty and our honour: We engaged to the people with him, and to the people for him, and from our hands they may juſtly expect a ſatisfaction of punishment, being they cannot have that of performance. What the people at preſent indure, and poſterity shall ſuffer, will be all laid at our doores: for onely we under God have the power to pull down this Dagon which we have ſet up. And if we doe it not, all mankinde will repute us Approovers of all the Villanyes he hath done: and authours of all to come. Shall we that would not endure a king attempting Tyranme, shall we ſuffer a profeſt Tyrant? We that reſiſted the Lyon aſſailing us,<note place="margin">Cic. in Epiſt. ad Octav.</note> shall we ſubmit to the Woolf tearing us? If there be no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy to be found, we have great reaſon to exclaime, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tinam te potius (Carole) retinuiſſemus quam hunc habuiſſemus, non quod ulla ſit optanda ſervitus, ſed quod exdignitate Domini minus turpis eſt conditio ſervi.</hi> We wish we had rather en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured thee (o Charles) then have been condemned to this meane Tyrant, not that we deſire any kinde of ſlavery, but that the quality of the Maſter ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing graces the condition of the ſlave.</p>
               <p>But if we conſider it rightly what our duty, our engagements, and our ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour exact from us, both our ſafety and our intereſt oblige us to, And tis as unanſwerable, in us, to diſcretion as tis to vertue, to let this viper live. For firſt he knowes very well tis onely we that have the power to hurt him, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of us he will take any courſe to ſecure himſelf: he is conſcious to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf how falſly and perfidiouſly he hath dealt with us, and therefore he will alwaies feare that from our revenge, which he knowes he hath ſo well deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
               <p>Laſtly he knowes our principles, how directlie contrarie they are to that Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrarie povver he muſt govern by, and therefore he may reaſonablie ſuſpect, that we that have alreadie ventured our lives againſt Tirannie, will alwaies have the Will, when we have the opportunitie, to doe the ſame again.</p>
               <p>Theſe conſiderations will eaſily perſwade him to ſecure himſelf of us, if we prevent him not, and ſecure our ſelves of him. He reades in his Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of Pietie (a) the Diviene Padron,<note place="margin">Mach. pr. c. <hi>5</hi>
                  </note> &amp;c. He that makes himſelf maſter of a citty, that hath been accouſtumed to Libertie, if he deſtroies it not, he muſt expect to be deſtroied by it. And we may reade too in the ſame Authour,
<pb facs="tcp:164183:10"/>and beleeve him, that<note n="(b)" place="margin">Ibid. c. <hi>3</hi>
                  </note> thoſe that are the occaſion that one becomes povver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; alvvaies ruine, that is, if they want the witt and courage to ſecure them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
               <p>Novv as to our intereſt, we muſt never expect that he vvill ever truſt thoſe, that he hath provoked and feares: He vvill be ſure to keep us down leaſt we should pluck dovvn him. Tis the rule that Tirants obſerve, vvhen they are in power never to make much uſe of thoſe that heipt them to it, and indeed tis their intereſt and ſecurity not to doe it: for thoſe that have been the authours of their greatneſſe being conſcious of their ovvn merit, they are bold vvith the Tirant and leſſe induſtrious to pleaſe him. They think all he can doe for them is their due, and ſtill they expect more: and vvhen they fail in their expectations, (as tis impoſsible to ſatisfie them) their diſappointments make them diſcontented, and their diſcontents dangerous. Therefore all Tirants follovv the example of Dionyſius, vvho vvas ſaid to uſe his friends, as he did his Bottles, vvhen he had uſe for them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e kept them by him, vvhen he had none, that they should not trouble him and lie in his vvay, he hung them up.</p>
               <p>But to conclude, This alreadie overlong Paper, let every man to vvhom God hath given the Spirit of Wiſdome and Courage, be perſvvaded by his Honour, his Safetie, his ovvn good and his Countries, and indeed the dutie he ovves to his Generation, and to Mankind, to endeavour by all Rational means to free the World of this Peſt. Let not other nations have the occaſion to think ſo meanelie of us, as if vve reſolved to ſit ſtill and have our Eares bored: or that any diſcouragement or diſappointments can ever make us deſiſt from attempting our Libertie till we nave purchaſed it, either by this Monſters death or by our own. Our nation is not yet ſo barren of vertue, that we want noble examples to follow amongſt our ſelves. The brave Sindercombe hath shewed as great a minde, as anie old Rome could boaſt of, and had he lived there, his name had been regiſtred with Brutus, and Cato; and he had had his Statues as well as they.</p>
               <p>But I will not have ſo ſiniſter an opinion of our ſelves (as little generoſitie as Slaverie hath left us) as to think ſo great a vertue can want its Monuments e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven amongſt us. Certainlie in every vertuous mind he e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re Statues rear'd to Sindercombe. When ever we reade the Elogies of thoſe that have died for their Countrie: when we admire thoſe great examples of magnanimitie, that have tired Tirants cruelties: VVhen we extoll their conſtancie, whom nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bribes nor terrours could make betray their Friends: Tis then we erect Sindercombe Statues, and grave him Monuments; VVhere all that can be ſaid of a great and noble minde, we juſtlie make an Epitaph for him. And though the Tirant cauſed him to be Smothered, leaſt the people should hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der an open murder; yet he will never be able either to ſmother his memorie, or his own Villanie. His poiſon was but a poore and common device to impoſe onely on thoſe that underſtood not Tirants practiſes, and are unacquainted (if any be) with his cruelties and falshoods. He may therefore if he pleaſe take away the Stake from Sindercombs Grave; and if he have a minde it should be known how he died, let him ſend thither the Pillowes and Feather-bedds with which Barkſtead and his Hangman ſmothered him. But to conclude, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et not this Monſter think himſelf the more ſecure that he hath ſuppreſt one
<pb facs="tcp:164183:11"/>great Spirit,<note n="(a)" place="margin">&amp; what may, Clccil and Toop ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect for their Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery an perjury?</note> he may be confident that, <hi>Longus poſt illum ſequitur or do idem petentium decus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ther's a great Rowle behinde, even of thoſe that are in his own muſter-Rowles, that are ambitious of the name of the Deliverers of their Countrey: and they know what the action is that will purchaſe it. His bed, his table is not ſecure, and he ſtands in need of other Guards to defend him againſt his own. Death and deſtruction purſues him where ever he goes: they follow him eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where,<note place="margin">Iob. <hi>20.</hi>
                  </note> like his fellow-travellers, and at laſt they will come upon him like armed men. Darkeneſſe is hid in his ſecret places, a Fire not blown shall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume him;<note place="margin">Whitehall. Hampton-court. &amp;c.</note> it shall goe ill with him that is left in his Tabernacle. He shall flee from the Iron weapon, and a bow of Steel shall ſtrike him through. Becauſe he hath oppreſſed, and forſaken the poore; becauſe he hath violently taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way a Houſe (a) which he builded not: We may be confident, and ſo may be, that ere long,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>v.</hi> 5.</note> all this will be accomplish't: For the Triumphing of the wicked is but short, and the joy of the Hypocrite but for a moment. Though his Excellencie<note n="(b)" place="margin">He hath now left that title for High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; and will shortly leave that for King.</note> mount up to the Heavens, and his Head reacheth unto the Clouds, yet he shall perish for ever like his own dung. They that have ſeen Him shall ſay, where is He.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <head>POSCRIPT.</head>
               <p>Curteous Reader, Expect another Sheet or two of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of this Subject, if I eſcape the Tyrants hands, although he gets (in the interim) the Crown upon his Head, which he hath (underhand) put his Confederates on to petition his acceptance thereof.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
